<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Alignment between properties">
   <intro href="/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/views/schema_explorer.html">
      <description>
         There are a lot of different functions to map schema elements. This tasks 
are about finding possible transformations between <b>source and target 
properties</b>.<br/><br/>
To this point, you should have found some semantically equal properties, or at least 
found some possible options for mandatory properties.<br/><br/>
This tasks will not approach the question on finding these pairs.<br/><br/>
The Help link (question mark upper right corner) opens the help to the 
Schema Explorer - view. Use it, if you want to know how to browse and interpret 
the current schema status.<br/><br/>
Read the tasks, to gain information and then try to perform them, if they fit the requirements. 
If you are not sure, at any point, continue with the next task. 
You can go back to a task, by clicking on the tasks Headline. 
(It will expand and you can reread it)
      </description>
   </intro>
   <item
         title="Alignment between properties - start"
         href="/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/concepts/what_is_alignment.html">
      <description>
         For types it is not so complicated to find the right access point for the 
transformation (see Alignment between types), but for properties it can be tricky, 
based on the schema complexity.<br/><br/>
If you are using <b>comma separated value</b> (*.csv) or <b>shape file</b> (*.shp) 
format as your source schema, or both loaded schema have only few types, you may skip the 
task &quot;Complex Schema&quot;. It provides more detailed information about 
browsing and finding properties within depth of inheritance.<br/><br/>
Also note, that every transformation function have only one target property (no variables) 
and you can't do more than one alignment at a time.
<br/><br/>
The Help link (question mark upper right corner) show more information about 
the concept of an alignment.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item
   		title="Three basic tasks"
   		href="/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/views/alignment.html">
   		<description>
   			Besides the <b>creation</b> of an alignment cell (created automatically after finishing 
a function wizard), it is possible to <b>edit</b> or <b>remove</b> the cell.<br/>
Click the right mouse button, on a alignment cell (the one with function name between 
source and target element cell) in the <b>Alignment - View</b>, to open some options.<br/>
The <b>Edit...</b> option will open the function wizard with your previously entered 
arguments, so you can edit them. Just finish the function wizard again, to update the cell.
<br/>
The <b>Delete</b> option will remove the cell. 
Pay attention to inheritance!
If you delete a inherited alignment cell (little blue up arrow besides the function name, 
in Alignment - View) 
this relation is deleted for every other Type, it was inherited to, as well.
<br/><br/>
The Help link (question mark upper right corner) of this task, will show you more 
information about the Alignment - View.
   		</description>
   </item>
   <item
   		title="Complex Schema"
   		skip="true"
   		href="/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/tasks/alignment/mapping_with_complex_schema.html">
   		<description>
   			<b>GML</b> (or related) Schema files or <b>XSD</b> (Extensible Markup Language 
(XML) Schema Definition) files support and can contain inheritance. There is a 
&quot;parent type&quot; (often abstract, red and cursive labeled) and one or more 
&quot;children type&quot;(s). The last children in the depth of inheritance should be 
concrete.<br/><br/>
The goal of this task is to show you, how you can save some work by using inherited 
properties.
Read the task if you want to do something like this:<br/>
TypeA.id -> Target.id<br/>
TypeB.id -> Target.id<br/>
TybeC.id -> Target.id<br/>
IF TypeA, TypeB and TypeC have the parent type AbstractType. And AbstractType has a 
property id (AbstractType.id) so it is same property for every child, 
than you can map AbstractType.id -> Target.id.<br/><br/>
<b>You could use this, if ...</b><br/>
...multiple context conditions defined on one source type. A Type with a context condition is a 
child of its source type.<br/>
...the one of the schema has attendance of depth of inheritance. e.g. a complex schema.<br/><br/>
The Help link (question mark upper right corner of this task) will provide more information about 
working with complex schema.
   		</description>
   	</item>
   	<item
   		title="Prepare for mapping: Hide unpopulated properties">
   		<description>
   			If you want to create an alignment for a special data set, you can do this. 
With this Editor, you can reuse this alignment within a project, with same source and target schema, 
as a base alignment.<br/><br/>
To have a better overview you can use the [o°o] (hide unpopulated properties) 
icon within the Schema explorer view, if you've loaded some source data. 
If you can't find a special property (in source or target schema), check if you have 
hidden the unpopulated properties (for this schema). It is recommended to do not hide 
target schema properties until the whole alignment process is finished.<br/>
In the default case, you can see all populated and unpopulated properties.<br/>
   		</description>
   		<subitem 
   			label="Choose to hide or not to hide unpopulated source properties.">
   		</subitem>
   	</item>
   	<item
   		title="Add condition context (CQL)"
   		href="/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/tasks/schema/define_context.html">
   		<description>
   		The Contextual Query Language (CQL) is used if you want to put instance 
transformation under condition. Note, that only data can have a condition.<br/><br/>
For example:<br/>
Does the Person type have the property Person.name (Does the person have a name)?<br/>
You would check on existence of a value for the Person.name property (e.g. value &lt;&gt; &quot;  
for string data type).<br/>
If you filter a value and it appears, the filter will pass &quot;No Value&quot; (golden font color in Data - View) 
as the function input for this value.<br/>
The Help link (question mark upper right corner) will give you more information about 
adding a context.<br/><br/>
		</description>
		<subitem 
   			label="Think about adding CQL filter. And add them, if needed.">
   		</subitem>
   	</item>
   	<item
   		title="Set priority">
   		<description>
   			You may encounter the problem, that you have one property 
separated into two ore more semantically equal properties. (You may have more than one 
value for this property, like a list of dates: date1, date2 and so on.)<br/><br/>

Case: You want both dates to be transformed.<br/>
In this case, you have to add an instance context for the tDate.<br/>
Do a click on with the right mouse button on the target property tDate. And 
choose &quot;Add instance context&quot;.<br/>
If the option is not available, the target schema must not have more instances. 
(Please check Properties - view -&gt; Constrains)<br/><br/>

Case: You can not have more than one instance but two or more properties.<br/>
In this case, you have to choose which one of the values (and so the properties) 
are most important for your transformation. You can have four max (lowest, low, 
normal=default and high priority).
Do the transformation as guided. Then click 
right mouse button on the alignment cell, choose &quot;Set Priority Level&quot; 
and then choose the level.<br/><br/>
It is recommended to add the condition (value &lt;&gt; X) to the source property, where X is any value 
declared as noValue (e.g. '', 0, 999, ) (e.g. value &lt;&gt; null). X depends on your source data and your source 
property.
   		</description>
   	</item>
   	<item
   		title="Where to start the alignment"
   		href="/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/tasks/alignment/mapping_schema_elem.html">
   		<description>
   			There are a lot of different transformations, categorized into <b>General, Geometry, 
Inspire, Numeric and Others</b>.<br/><br/>
Select a pair of properties (remember, that there do not have to be a source property) 
and click on the blue arrow between the two schema trees. You will get a selection of 
possible functions in random order.<br/><br/>
To start an alignment, click on the source and target property, click on the blue arrow between them, 
and select the desired function. To undo a selection click on the element. 
Do deselect an element hold [CTRL] and click on the selected element. 
If you click on an unselected source schema element while holding [CTRL], you can add this to the 
selection (multiple select). Note, that only proper functions are displayed, when 
using the blue arrow between source and target schema. More than one source property works for 
additional parameters, like variables. (the element can be any property)<br/><br/>
If you start to perform a function, 
you will see a new (smaller) window. Tasks refer to this window as the function wizard.<br/>
The title of the function wizard shows you the current used function.<br/>
The first page is always about the selected elements and needed entities (elements).<br/>
You can choose a different property by clicking on the suitable field.<br/><br/>
The Help link (question mark upper right corner) will provide more information 
on how basic alignment is done.
   		</description>
   	</item>
   	<item
   		title="Assign function"
   		href="/eu.esdihumboldt.cst.doc.functions/functions/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.align.assign.html">
   		<description>
   			<b>The Assign function</b><br/>
On the second page (click next&gt; at the first page of the function wizard), you can 
enter the value you want to assign. Note, that the value is the same for every 
instance! Sometimes you can not enter a value, but choose a predefined one. 
(Called Enumerations)<br/>
If there is no predefined value and you do not know, what to enter as a parameter, you 
should have a look at the description (Properties-View) for the target property.<br/><br/>
If you have selected a source property and 
start an assignment, this source property becomes an <b>anchor</b>. This means, that the 
assignment will be performed, if the source property has a value. 
(Note, that null is a value.) This is important in combination with a CQL filter. If you filter 
a value and that value appear, the filter will pass &quot;No Value&quot; (golden font color in Data - View) 
as the functions input. An assign with a filtered source property as an anchor, will be performed 
on every value, except the filtered one.<br/>
<br/><br/>
The Help link (question mark upper right corner) will give you information 
about the assign function.
   		</description>
   	</item>
   	<item
   		title="General function Rename"
   		href="/eu.esdihumboldt.cst.doc.functions/functions/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.align.rename.html">
   		<description>
   			If they have the same data type and you do not want or have to edit the value, you can 
simply <b>Rename</b> the given properties.<br/>
<b>The Rename function</b> is a function is limited to one source and one target property. 
If you have multiple source properties, for the same target property, you can't use rename 
without some preparations.<br/>
<br/>
You can rename a geometry, too. If the geometry is defined in a standard (e.g. GML) you can 
save some work. In this case, the source and target geometry have the same structure. 
On the second page of the Rename function wizard, choose true for the structural rename. 
This option tries to do a rename for every equal child property. 
No cells will be created due to this process, so you have to check the correctness of 
this transformation by yourself. 
If you loaded some data and have live transformation activated, you should see 
for every instance of the property, there is one instance of the child property (if the 
values are not filtered).<br/><br/>
Select one pair of properties, do the alignment and then repeat.<br/><br/>
The Help link of this task shows you the overview about the rename function.
   		</description>
   	</item>
   	<item
   		title="Calculate and Build Strings">
   		<description>
   		<b>The Mathematical Expression function</b><br/>
Use this on a selected properties, where only numbers appear as data type, 
and enter an mathematical expression on the second function wizard page. 
If you have one or more source property selected, you can use its value as a variable.<br/><br/>
Example of use is the conversion from yards to meter. (In this case, please pay attention 
to unit of measurement (uom) properties)<br/><br/>

<b>The Formatted String function</b><br/>
Use this function if you want to format a value to a String. Every selected source property 
will be set as a variable. On the second page of the function wizard, you can add these 
source properties to the String with a double click. ({variable} &lt;- in braces)<br/>
If you use variables, you get a string for every instance. It is recommended to treat this 
with caution, if you merged the type, of the variable property, 
to a target schema type and use formatted String between them. Only use this, if the number 
of source and target instances are equal. If not, and you want to assign a special 
string for every target instance (more than one), you should use the classification 
on the property you used for the merge.
<br/>
If you want one static string, you should use the Assign function.
   		</description>
   	</item>
   	<item
   		title="The Geometric functions">
   		<description>
   			If you want to map the source geometry 1:1 to the target property, you can choose the 
rename function. Remember, that in default case, the child properties are not mapped automatically.
<br/><br/>
Do you have a Line geometry, like a path on a street or a river, but want to or need to  
be represented by a surface, you can use the <b>Network Expansion</b> function.<br/>
You have different options how to use this function. The function need a geometry and 
a number. This can be a property (for example the width of the river) with a mathematical 
expression (the measurement has to be meter (m) so you can convert the values at this point). 
Select the variable property (a second property within the source schema) by holding [CTRL] 
and click on it, so you should have both, the geometry and its &quot;width&quot;, 
and the target geometry selected yet.<br/><br/>
Use <b>Compute Extent</b> if you want something like a collection of all geometry for 
a given type. You choose between a bounding box, a convex hull or union. (low detailed to 
high detailed geometry as a result)<br/><br/>
Have a close look to what you need and what you have. Sometimes the properties share the name 
but not the structure or semantically equal meaning. And you can't map them directly. 
Look out for &quot;Choice&quot; and other properties, with a group symbol (a little package).
		</description>
   	</item>
   	<item
   		title="Classification function">
   		<description>
   			This function is often used between code lists. (Reclassification)<br/>
One example of use is, if you have a pair and you could simply use a rename, that you 
have to do a localization within the Mapping.<br/><br/>
Click on source and target property, and choose Classification transformation.<br/>
You can build your own look up tables. (A table with the form: source value -&gt; target Value)<br/> 
Or have a previously build one. You can choose local one (*.csv file) or load a file from 
an external resource (http://...).<br/><br/>
<b>Local file</b>
If you want to use a local look up table, you choose Manual tab on the second function 
wizard page and click on the little folder icon. 
Choose your file and follow the instructions. After everything is done, your 
values will be imported and you can see them in the Manual tab. You can edit them 
by clicking on the table cell or you can click finish to create the alignment cell.<br/>
   		</description>
   	</item>
</cheatsheet>
