<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Create mappings">
   <intro>
      <description>
Welcome to the tutorial to create some mappings.<br />
It will load an example project and guide you through renaming attributes.<br />
      </description>
   </intro>
   <item
         title="Load example">
      <action
            class="eu.esdihumboldt.hale.ui.firststeps.LoadProjectAction"
            pluginId="eu.esdihumboldt.hale.ui.firststeps"
            param1="false"
            param2="/exampleschema/t1t2.halex"
            param3="bundle"
            param4="eu.esdihumboldt.hale.ui.firststeps"
            required="true">
      </action>
      <description>
Click on <b>Click to perform</b> to load the example project.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Add missing alignments">
      <description>
Use the <b>Schema Explorer</b> to explore the source and target schema.
Each contains a type that is semantically equal to the one from the other schema, but has a different structure.
The schema elements that are not highlighted are not mapped yet.
To complete the alignment, add the missing relations.<br />
Select them in <b>Edit&#8594;Add relation...&#8594;General&#8594;Rename</b> and click <b>Finish</b>,
or select them directly in the Schema Explorer, click the arrow in between, click <b>Rename</b>
and then <b>Finish</b> in the opened dialog. <br />
<br />
Note, that you are mapping a simple type to a complex nested type. You are done, if you found the two missing alignments.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Save the transformation result">
      <action
            pluginId="eu.esdihumboldt.hale.ui.firststeps"
            class="eu.esdihumboldt.hale.ui.firststeps.ImportAction"
            param1="eu.esdihumboldt.hale.io.instance.write.transformed"
            required="false" /> 
      <description>
The project includes a small sample source data set.
You can use the <b>Source Data</b> view and the <b>Transformed Data</b> view in the <b>Data</b> perspective to inspect the source instances and the transformed instances that are created based on the alignment.<br />
<br />
To export the transformed instances to a XML file, select <b>File&#8594;Export&#8594;Transformed data...</b>.
Then select <b>XML (Custom root element)</b> as export format and continue with <b>Next</b>. You may now specify a target file and whether it should be validated on completion.
On the next page, select the <b>collection</b> element as root element for the file and press finish.<br />
<br />
If you added the mapping for <b>city</b> in the previous step, the validator will report success after the file has been written. 
      </description>
      <onCompletion>
Congratulations, you added mappings to an existing project, now continue with your own project!
      </onCompletion>
   </item>
</cheatsheet>
