<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Start with the Types and feature Types">
   <intro href="/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/views/schema_explorer.html">
      <description>
         A Type is part of a Schema.<br/>
It is marked with a <b>[ft] or [T]</b> symbol in the Schema Explorer. A red cursive [ft] or [T] means an abstract feature type and blue means a concrete one.<br/>
A [ft] schema element is a GML AbstractFeatureType. [T] are own defined types.<br/>
[+] stand for an expandable type/object/element, so there are sub level elements you may analyze, too, to find the right target for an alignment. 
In standard Schema Explorer View (default) you get shown all mappable types as a list.<br/><br/>
For this task, the only thing you need to do, is to identify the concrete (blue) <b>[ft]</b> and <b>[T]</b> symbols in the <b>Schema Explorer</b>-View.<br/>
Click the little question mark on the right upper corner to get some help. In this case to the Schema Explorer-View.
      </description>
   </intro>
   <item
   		title="Configure the mappable Types"
   		href="/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/tasks/schema/mapping_relevant.html">
   	<description>
   		You should identify what types are mapping relevant or you want 
to use. (You need a source and target schema to do this.) <br/><br/>
Configure the Types now or do it later, it clears up the Schema Explorer View.<br/>
If you have only few Types, right-click (right mouse button) on a type and choose &quot;Exclude Type from mapping&quot;. 
To undo your last action, hold [CTRL] and press [z] on your keyboard. It will also bring back the last 
excluded Type.<br/><br/>
The Help Link in the upper right corner, of this task, will give you a guide to do the customization.
   	</description>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Find (at least) two matching types.">
      <description>
         To find two matching types is the task, but how is it done?<br/>
Two matching types mean, that one type (feature Type or Type) of the source schema and one type 
(feature Type or Type) of the target schema are alike or somehow related.<br/>
So, first we need to find all pairs, because the main part of the alignment is done between two elements.<br/>
One Type can be part of more than one alignment, but the alignments will be performed separately.<br/>
An example: (there is only one Customer Type listed in the Schema Explorer-View)<br/>
Source		-> Target Schema<br/>
[T] Person  -> [T] Customer<br/>
[T] Address -> [T] Customer<br/>
or vice versa:<br/>
Source		-> Target Schema<br/>
[T] Customer-> [T] Person<br/>
[T] Customer-> [T] Address<br/><br/>
Analyze the target schema types and try to find semantically equal type(s) in your source schema.<br/><br/>
Some hints on finding types:<br/>
      </description>
   <subitem 
   		label="Think about alternative names and/or translations for the target type in your source schema.">
   </subitem>
   <subitem 
   		label="Differ between meaning and naming. (e.g. what is the meaning of this type)">
   </subitem>   
   <subitem 
   		label="Read the Description within the General tab at the Properties-View, while the target type is blue selected.">
   </subitem>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Select the first two Types.">
      <description>
         Now you can imagine how the first steps for the alignment may look like.<br/>
<b>Select</b> the first pair. To do so, you click (left mouse button) on the type.<br/><br/>
Start by selecting the first element. It could be the source or the target type.<br/>
Then select the opposite type.<br/><br/>
The clicked element gets highlighted. The active selected element has a dark blue background color. 
The passive (but also selected) element gets a light gray background color. (There can be more passive and no active selection)<br/>
To undo a selection, hold the [CTRL] key and click (left mouse button) on the element. 
Click (left mouse button) on one element (without holding any key) and it will become the only selected Element.
      </description>
   </item>
</cheatsheet>
