<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Properties">
   <intro href = "/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/reference/schema_elements.html">
      <description>
         Properties are schema elements and are a part of a type or feature type.<br/>
They have different data types and divided into [8] numbers, [=] string, [o] geometry and [;.] objects.<br/><br/>
Use the Schema Explorer View. Use the [+] marks to expand the element to display more properties.<br/><br/>
The Help (question mark on the upper right corner of this task) will provide more detailed information about schema elements.
      </description>
   </intro>
   <item
         title="How to analyze schema for properties" href="/eu.esdihumboldt.hale.doc.user/html/views/properties.html">
      <description>
         To identify an alignment between the source and the target schema you can search for semantic comparable schema elements. 
You should have a look at the <b>Properties-View</b>, too.
(click on question mark for more information).<br/><br/>
If you select an element and then click on the Properties-View, you get an overview over the selected property (or element). 
The Headline tells you what property you are looking at. At the <b>General</b> tab, you get some info, like the <b>Description</b>.
(This Description is part of the schema file)<br/><br/>
It is recommended to look at <b>target properties</b>, because the source Schema 
can have more properties than you need for the mapping. And as a part of the harmonization process, it is not possible to change 
the target schema at this moment.<br/>
You can not create more than one alignment cell at a time, but sometimes the transformation functions need, 
or can have additional variables (one or more source properties). 
For the analysis phase, you do not need to identify the variables, because you need to know 
about the transformations first. (see Alignment between properties - cheat sheet)
<br/><br/>
But vice versa there can be some target schema elements, you can't map, because the required property does not exist in the source schema.<br/>
The lack of a matching source schema elements can be part of the mapping and is sometimes a valid condition. 
Future tasks will show you, how to deal with those cases (see Assign function in Alignment between properties - cheat sheet). 
 	 </description>
   </item>
   <item
   		 title="How to select a pair, begin with mandatory">
   	  <description>
   	  Begin with a target property that is <b>mandatory</b> (it has a red * in the right upper corner).<br/><br/>
Now, look for a corresponding source property and select it. (Remember, that elements shaded in grey and blue(active) are selected.)<br/>
A starting Point can be the geometry, an example:<br/>
Target = standard geometry ([o] with a green arrow and a red *)<br/>
Source = geometry or the_geom<br/><br/>
Pay Attention to identifier, because there are different types of them. Maybe a localId like a 
consecutive numbering of data without special meaning, or it can be a unique identifier, 
like a GML id or some id you can refer to. The id property can be 
a link to another schema types property as well. (e.g. a reference to a Document for the data)<br/><br/>
The &quot;data type&quot; can be an indication of a corresponding property. (like a date data type to a date data type)<br/><br/>
Think about some alternative names and translations for the target property (in the language of the source schema).<br/><br/>
Here is a basic check list:<br/>
   	  </description>
   	  <subitem 
   	  		label ="Search for a property with a similar data type. (e.g. date and date)">
   	  </subitem>
   	  <subitem 
   	  		label ="Is there a similar name, in the source schema, for one of the alternative names? (e.g. geometry(target) and the_geom(source))">
   	  </subitem>
   	  <subitem 
   	  		label ="Differ between meaning and naming. (e.g. what is the meaning of this id?)">
   	  </subitem>
   	  <subitem 
   	  		label ="Remember, that a missing source property is a valid condition.">
   	  </subitem>
   </item>
</cheatsheet>
